<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The famous history of George Lord Faukonbridge, bastard son to Richard Cordelion King of England Begotten in his royal tower, vpon the princely Clarabel, daughter to Don Iohn Duke of Austria, surnamed the worldes faire concubine. Shewing his knightly adventures, dignified victories, with his life and death, spent in the honor of God and his countrey: never wearing any other garmet, but that lyons skinne, by which his kingly father challenged his lyon-like title.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10709</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118329</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853536</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853536</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18921</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00574)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18921)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 885:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The famous history of George Lord Faukonbridge, bastard son to Richard Cordelion King of England Begotten in his royal tower, vpon the princely Clarabel, daughter to Don Iohn Duke of Austria, surnamed the worldes faire concubine. Shewing his knightly adventures, dignified victories, with his life and death, spent in the honor of God and his countrey: never wearing any other garmet, but that lyons skinne, by which his kingly father challenged his lyon-like title.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 39 [i.e. 43], [1]  p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By I. B[eale] and are to be sold by Iames Dauies, at his shop neere Fleet Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The famous historie of Lord Faukonbridge.</note>
                  <note>Some pages missing in number only.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut on title page (and on page 43 verso).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18921:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18921:1"/>
            <p>The Famous Hiſtory of GEORGE Lord FAVKONBRIDGE, Baſtard Son to RICHARD CORDELION, KING OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Begotten in his royal Tower, vpon the princely <hi>Clarabel,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Don Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>The Worldes faire Concubine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shewing his Knightly Aduentures, dignified Victories, with his Life and death, ſpent in the honor of GOD and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: Neuer wearing any other Garment, but that <hi>Lyons Skinne,</hi> by which his Kingly Father challenged his Lyon-like Title.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>I. B.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Iames Danie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> at his ſhop neere Fleet Conduit. 1616.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18921:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18921:2"/>
            <head>THE FAMOVS Hiſtory of GEORGE Lord FAVKONBRIDGE, Baſtard ſonne to <hi>RICHARD CORDELION</hi> King of England.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. How <hi>Richard Cordelion</hi> King of England, going to the holy Land, ſlew <hi>Phillip</hi> the Prince of Auſtria, and how <hi>Don Iohn</hi> doomed him to a moſt ſtrange puniſhment, and of his wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full lamentation in priſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the true ſpirits of illuſtrious atchieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, poſſeſt the Nobility of Europe, and that the Babes of honour, fed vpon the milke of Knightly aduentures, here raigned in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, a royall minded King, named <hi>Richard Cordelion,</hi> a Prince repleniſhed with the commendable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of renowne, in whoſe gouernement, both Armes and Art flouriſhed, warres wrought peace, and peace brought happineſſe. In this Kings time, the bleſſed ſtate of Gods holy City of Ieruſalem, groaned vnder the heauy yoke of Paganiſme, and the deſpiſed Infidels with pride and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuppreſſed all her royalties, for recouery whereof, all Chriſtendome tooke Armes, and the rumors of warre wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully thundered in all our Northerne Nations.</p>
               <p>Fiue Chriſtian Kings, (vnder the bloody ſtanders of <hi>Godfrey</hi> of Bullin,) (that imperious Monarks, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the World) marched. Amongſt which glorious num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, one matchles King, <hi>Richard Plantaginet,</hi> was too aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous forward, for he in the blooming bud of his youth, with the chiefeſt Chiualry of England, cloathed in ſtéele, fired with
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18921:3"/> fame and full of reſolution, left the gouernment of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to his brother <hi>Iohn,</hi> then Duke of Ireland, and arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in Auſtria, the méeting place of theſe Chriſtian Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates.</p>
               <p>The reſt of this Campe royall, not then in a readineſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtomes of Princes, cauſed King <hi>Richard</hi> to requeſt entertainement for him and his Knights. <hi>Don Iohn</hi> then Duke of Auſtria, being a Prince ſo curteous and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he could doe no leſſe then grant it. Now Fame and Fortune in King <hi>Richards</hi> thoughts ſmiled, and the ſmooth brow of wiſhed good ſpéed, bad him and his hundred Knights welcome.</p>
               <p>A hundred he had as then for his guard, called Knights of the Bath, a title of dignity firſt giuen by this King: but now while the reſt of his Army planted their ſtanders vpon the downes adioining to the Court, theſe Knightly Gallants ſo reuelled in the Dukes Pallace, that well were they that could purchaſe their fauours, and highly graced were all ſuch as had but the ſmalleſt imployment of an Engliſh Knight.</p>
               <p>So amiable, pleaſing, and curteous, were the conditions of King <hi>Richard</hi> and his followers, ſo truely were their minds deuoted to honour, that they euen inforced loue from all eſtates, the haughty minded of their own accords became gentle, the ſtubborne nature pliable, and the frowne of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Engliſh brow by deſert challenged both cap and knée, <hi>Don Iohn</hi> himſelfe began to grow diſgracious, his Subiects wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, alegiance waxed cold, and none but the name of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Richard</hi> merited Fortunes high graces: All Auſtria eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med England a happy Nation, by nature the darling of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the only hopes of Chriſtendome, ſo grealy are ſtill the fauors of our Engliſh people in the eies of forren kingdoms.</p>
               <p>This detracted loue of his ſubiects did not a little diſpleaſe <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> and his ſon Prince <hi>Phillip,</hi> and no little enuy by it were bred in their two fired breaſts, that nothing could quench the increaſing flame therof, but King <hi>Richards</hi> ſhame and confuſion. Politicke and cloſe were their purpoſes,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18921:3"/> deadly and diuelliſh their intents, and moſt vnhumane and vnchriſtian like their procéedings, the law of Armes was quite laid aſide, the honor of Princes forgotten, and the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Knight hood vilely abuſed, malice, and wrath, the champions of pale death hourely poſſeſſed their two hearts, with a ſecret imagination of vengeance, plotted againſt the life of royall <hi>Richard,</hi> to murther by violence, would but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre diſpleaſures of forren Nations, to kill innocents offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Heauen, and to betray Princes, hath rewards in hell, a thouſand thouſands of diſpleaſing motions, diſquieted their diſcontented mindes, diſhonoured as they thought by the vertues of King <hi>Richard,</hi> diſgrace boyling in her grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt heart, could no longer be ſuppreſſed, but néeds the flames of fury muſt breake forth, and a flattering practiſe of reuenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment mollifie their intollerable torments, and in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was it accompliſhed.</p>
               <p>Prince <hi>Phillip</hi> the onely ſonne and heire apparant to <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> the pride and hopes of Auſtria, in whoſe life and good Fortune conſiſteth his countries honor, like a deſperate and prodigall gallant, in a diſſembling ſhape of friendſhip, challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged King <hi>Richard</hi> at a Princely turnament, and in the knightly games of tilting, perſonally to combat hand to hand, the Engliſh King in the Aprill of his man-hood, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing inferior in proweſſe to Prince <hi>Phillip,</hi> hauing the ſparkes of Maieſty glowing in his boſome, in a moſt prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner accepted his challenge, and againſt the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, prouided al things fitting for ſo noble an enterpriſe.</p>
               <p>Time with his lazy wings, ſéemed to fly too ſlowly, and to croſſe the forward attempts of theſe youthfull combitants, each minute ſéemed an houre, each houre a day, and each day a moneth, till the appointed time came of this royall turna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo bold, forward, and illuſtrious were theſe martialiſts, the one ſtriuing for honor, the other for reuenge.</p>
               <p>I néed not here ſpeake of the ſumptuous preparations, the excéeding charge, and coſtly habilliments prouided againſt that day, numberleſſe were the eye-witneſſes of this Court-like
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18921:4"/> paſtime, ready prepared to bid them welcome with a gracious applauſe. To come to the fulneſſe of this glory, the day approched, the morning Sunne chéerefully roſe with a bright ſmile, the chriſtall Skie put on her faireſt robe, and the moderate aire ſéemed to further their procéedings, all things by nature were as furtherers to ſummon them to Armes, <hi>Don Iohn</hi> himſelfe attended by his greateſt Nobility, ſate as Vmpiers in the caſe, and each Lady with a prepared eye, was ready to cenſure of their deſerts, the tilting place being rayled in quadrangle-wiſe, round about beſet with lofty gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries, whereon people in degrees were placed in ſuch multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, as memory it ſelfe could hardly number: the Sunne beames had not more motes by imagination, then this thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpectators, equally wiſhing good fortune to them both, bright honors ſceane being ready to begin, the Drums and Trumpets gaue warning of the two combitants approch, in ſuch a melodious manner, as both aire and earth reſounded, the firſt that entered the liſtes, was Prince <hi>Phillip</hi> in a black capariſon, his horſe betrapt with ſable, his beuer cloſe, made of the faſhion of a flying Griffon, his Launce and Scutchion borne before him by a naked Indian, all agréeable to his blacke deſires: for the ſtéeled point of his Launce, and the kéen edge of his ſword, were both impoiſoned; his motto was, <hi>True honour hath no equall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Immediately after entered <hi>Richard</hi> of England, mounted vpon a Spaniſh Gennet, as milke white and ſpotles as were his thoughts, his Armor bright and gliſtering, his Helmet of the faſhion of a ſunne ſparkeling fire, expreſſing both malice and mercy. Vpon his breaſt he had the honorable red croſſe of England, platted with Arabian ſilke, his Motto was; <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour tainted, in vaine repented.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus all things in readines for this royall turnament, the chéerefull reports of relentleſſe Drums and Trumpets, thundred a charge, whereupon the two couragious Princes, fired with reſolution, ſo fiercely aſſailed each other, that a ſtrange admiration of their man-hoods poſſeſſed all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18921:4"/> The old Duke <hi>Don Iohn</hi> himſelfe, ſitting with a longing deſire of his ſonnes victory, was immediatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented wich the ſpight of Fortune, for after he had woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Engliſh Prince with his impoiſoned weapons, to the great danger of life, couragious <hi>Richard</hi> expreſſing his Lion-like nature, cloſed Prince <hi>Phillip</hi> with ſuch a manly power, that with his heauy courtelax, at one blow he broke his necke: Folly it were to reſiſt deſtiny, for euen at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant he yéelded vp the ghoſt, and in the ſight of his old fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imbraced death.</p>
               <p>This ſudden accident aduanced not ſo much the honours of King <hi>Richard,</hi> as it ſetled fury in <hi>Don Iohns</hi> heart, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing loſt the hopes of his Kingdome, his onely ſonne and glory of his age, like a man deſperate of all good fortune, ioy, and conſolation, he raged both againſt heauen and earth, blaſpheming his Creator, ſwearing both by God and the world, that the treaſures of Europe ſhould not redeeme King <hi>Richards</hi> life, nor the vnknowne treaſures of the déepe Ocean (were they laid at his féet) preſerue him from a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable death: for (quoth he) in looſing my Sonne, the ſight of the World diſpleaſeth me, I will pine in griefe, I will fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh with woe, I will liue foodleſſe, féeding vpon nothing, but deſires of vengeance. Aſſiſt me thou ſpirit of deſtruction, that in wrath I may confound the murtherer of my ſonne, in whoſe life I more delighted, then in my royall crown: for in wanting him, I liue as a forlorne, wofull, and depoſed King, exild and baniſht from this worlds royalty: my ſecond ſoule adores the ſmalleſt drop of thy déere harts blood, ſhal be quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanced with the purple goa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of King <hi>Richards</hi> boſome. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpoken theſe, or ſuch like wordes, he commanded the Marſhall of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> to take the Engliſh Prince vnto his charge, and to kéepe him cloſe priſoner in a ſquare Tower of Marble ſtone, adioining to the vttermoſt part of his Court, and likewiſe to diſcharge all the followers of his Countrey, vpon paine of death not any one of them to bée ſéen in his territories after the date of ſeuen daies. All which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18921:5"/> according to the angry Dukes command, was by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall ſpéedily accompliſhed, the wofull King he to priſon, and his ſorrowfull followers to their natiue countrey, where his loyall Subiects made not a little moane for his hard miſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; <hi>Don Iohn</hi> with his Nobility mourned as grieuouſly for Prince <hi>Phillip,</hi> whom in moſt ſolemne manner they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred in a Princely Tombe, where we will leaue him ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in peace, and perſeuere in this our wofull Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>King <hi>Richard</hi> hauing now neither Crowne, Kingdome, nor liberty, but (by his late receiued wounds, from Prince <hi>Phillips</hi> poiſoned weapons,) lay bléeding in priſon, to his liues greateſt danger, and being deſtitute of friends, and all hopes of recouery, he dolefully breathed out this lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Oh vniuſt Fortune (ſaid hee) why in the prime of youth haſt thou thus deceiued me, and by thy flattering promiſes of aduancement thus betraied my Knightly aduentures? Thoſe bleſſed warres, where the ſtandard of Chriſt by their incouraging flouriſhes, makes cowards inconquerable, muſt by mee bee forſaken, and my vnhappy daies by <hi>Don Iohns</hi> vnprincely doome, haue ending, ſweat with teares.</p>
               <p>Oh you ingrateful wals, that with your pittileſſe bounds claſpes in a royall Prince; mercileſſe woe like a cruell ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant féedes vpon my heart, and the ſunne ſhine of delightfull conſolation is now for euer dimmed with the blacke cloudes of deſpaire, baniſht be all hopes of liberty, and the freedome that attends on Kings, is curbed with the baſe pennance of captiuity: Farre more fortunate is the humble eſtate of the Plow-mans life, he ſuffers onely the croſſe of priuate diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, when principalities indure the generall ſcandall of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, wherein Kingdomes, and the glory of Diadems, loſe their illuſtrious dignities. Where are now all my courtly traines of ſtarre-bright Nobility, my attendant followers, my gardiants, and humble ſeruitors, my pompous ſtate, roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all banquetings, and delightful muſicke, all ſo my ſoules eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall griefe, now vaniſhed, and conuerted into continuall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18921:5"/> no fellowſhip haue I to comfort me, but diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſighes, and melancholy diſpaire: Care is my food, and teares my drinke, nothing but the imaginations of woe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepts all hopes of fréedome.</p>
               <p>Oh vnhappy England, thou nurſe and mother of my life, diſhonoured in thy Kings diſgraces, and made moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by this iniurious and moſt vnprincely dealings, Heauen I hope with blacke vengeance, deadlier then the feare of hell, will in time ſpie out a moſt dreadfull quittance, written in the bloody brow of a curſed <hi>Austria,</hi> ſtained with inhumane murther of a King, whoſe death the child as yet vnborne ſhall rew, and after ages ſhall ſpeake off: pitty my diſtreſſes thou reuenger of mankind, that my ſoule may ſléepe in peace, and reſt in that bleſſed manſion prepared for Monarches.</p>
               <p>Theſe or ſuch like heart-breaking complaints being brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed from his grieued boſome, the paine of his impoiſoned wounds ſo inraged, and ſo furiouſly tormented his body yet bléeding that (poore King,) he fell into a ſwound, liueleſſe, and breathles, ſauing a little panting breath moued in his breaſt, a ſigne that the ſparkes of life were not quite extinguiſhed. But now, euer as this ſudden trance aſſailed King <hi>Richard,</hi> there entered into the priſon the Lord Marſhall, vnder whoſe charge he was then kept, where when to his great amaſement he beheld as he ſuppoſed, the King bereft of life, hauing a mind framed of a noble diſpoſition, began to pitty his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, and to accuſe his Lord and Maſter of iniuſtice, whereupon according to his gentle nature, hee dreſſed his wounds with a precious kind of balme, by nature ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, that it not onely recouered life, but alſo health, and in leſſe then in three daies, made him as ſound as he was before his combat with Prince <hi>Phillip,</hi> where we ſhall leaue King <hi>Richard,</hi> making his praiers to heauen for his deliuery from death, and ſpeake of other accidents that followed hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18921:6"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. How the two Engliſh Earles of <hi>Arundell</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly comforted King <hi>Richard</hi> in priſon, of the loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him, and <hi>Clarabella</hi> the Dukes daughter; how he how hee pulled out the Lyons heart, and thereby came to bee called <hi>Richard Cordelion,</hi> and of other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to the heauy and bitter command of the angry Duke, (in reuenge of his ſonnes death,) the Nobility and Knights of <hi>England</hi> departed <hi>Don Iohns</hi> Kingdome, leauing the wofull King in priſon, as aſhamed of ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a voiage, where being no ſooner come, and the reports thereof bruted in the eares of the Earles of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundell</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> but like two Engliſh ſpirited gallants, not able to brooke this forraine diſgrace, they reſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted England, proteſting either to bring their Soueraigne Lord ſafely to his Kingdome, or to leaue their bodies buried in <hi>Auſtria:</hi> that blood (quoth they) ſpent in the honour of our King and Countrey, is the ſweet ſacrifice of Knight-hood, and the true vermillion colour, that beautifies the rich robes of honour.</p>
               <p>Thus nobly minded, they with all ſpeed croſſed the Seas, which they were ioyfull off; ſo with ſo glorious a burthen, and the whiſling wind, proud of theſe Princely reſolued Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, louing kind, and loyall, ſet open their gentle portals, and beyond the expectation of man, ſet them ſafely vpon the coſts of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> where being no ſooner come, but they attired them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the diſguiſed habits of Fryers, the moſt ſecret, and fitteſt pollicy to attaine the wiſhed preſence of their impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18921:6"/> King, and by that meanes thought they to relieue him, if his extremity ſo much required; ſo comming to the priſon gate in a profeſſed zeale, as they ſaid they had of King <hi>Richards</hi> ſoules health: they deſired acceſſe, and that the Lord Marſhall would admit them to the Kings preſence, who being a man of a curteous nature, could doe no leſſe then grant their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, being ſo honeſt and vertuous a demand.</p>
               <p>Frowning Fortune beganne now a little to ſmile, and a little to eaſe his languiſhing ſorrowes: for no ſooner had his gentle eies caſt their dimme ſights (almoſt blinded with teares) vpon his two deare friends, but a ſudden reioycing hope aſſailed his heart, and like a royotous heire newly poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his patrimony, ſurfetted in pleaſure, all diſpairing paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the delightfull preſence of theſe two Engliſh Earles, were immediatly conuerted into iollity, their imbraces were as the cloſes of new married Damſels, where the extremity of ioy ſo ſwelled in their boſomes, that euen their eyes diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led teares, (and their hearts as it were danced.) Theſe two ſuppoſed Friers had no other Oriſons, but comfortable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports from his loyall Subiects in England: their Bookes were their loues, and their Beades their fealties.</p>
               <p>Thus in this ſecret manner vnſuſpected of any, repaired they daily to this diſtreſſed King, expecting hourely his liues metamorphoſes, either of liberty or death: Freedome, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, royalty, or captiuity: in which wauering doubt, while theſe three ſubiects of ſorrow remained, the diſpleaſed Duke (ſtill harbouring in his heart blacke malice, called a counſell of flattering ſicophants, ſuch as be ſtill the attendants of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narkes, where againſt both the law of Armes and Nations, it was decreed that King <hi>Richard</hi> ſhould combate with a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which if he ouercame, his liberty thereby might be purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; but being ouercome, he ſhould endure the ſharpe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this mercileſſe beaſt, whoſe greateſt fauour were but death: vpon which pittileſſe doome, this bloody coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l concluded, and thereupon appointed the time and houre, to the extreame griefe of many thouſadns, whoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18921:7"/> whoſe gentle harts euen trembled at this remorſleſſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But now marke the difference in nature of a cruel Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and a kind Child; the Father mercileſſe, the Child mild, the Father proud, the Child humble, the Father vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the Child reaſonable, the Father cruell, the Child louing, betwixt whom tyranny and remorſe ſtrous for ſuperiority: for <hi>Don Iohn</hi> bore not more extreame hate againſt the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh King, then his daughter faire <hi>Clarabella</hi> extended loue: In her heart partiall <hi>Cupid</hi> builded his Bower, and pitty with his ſmooth countenance, ſent dumbe meſſengers to the diſtreſſed King, which were modeſt ſighes, baſhfully ſent from her maiden-like breaſt, fearing to offend in affecting her Fathers enemy: yet loue, which hath commanded euen the Gods themſelues, and ſtill blindly leades earthly Monarkes with vnequall affections, making no difference betwixt Kings and Beggars, ſo ruled the deſires of diuine <hi>Clarabell,</hi> that ſhée wiſhed no other conſolation in this world, but the ſacred loue of Engliſh <hi>Richard;</hi> whoſe preſence (if ſhée might poſſeſſe) were to her ſoule as the pleaſures of Paradice: duty and obedience (by nature her Fathers right) were now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed into deſire and loue; the Princely behauiour of King <hi>Richard</hi> guided her thoughts, and (though as yet vnknowne to him) intangled her loue-ſicke heart in the toiles of <hi>Venus,</hi> wherein was no hope of recouery, but the vniting of them both in the equality of deſire. Theſe were faire <hi>Clarabels</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, which as an vncurable wound, diſmembred all the liuely wiſhes of virginity, offending onely in thought, and with the chilling feare of her ſecond ſolues deſtruction, by the terrible cenſure of her angry Father, ſhée grew like madde <hi>Medea,</hi> lunaticke and diſtraught, expecting the ſauage mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of royall <hi>Richard,</hi> ſhée railed both at Heauen and Earth, conſpiring thus againſt all her good Fortunes: For in loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him (quoth ſhée) the bloome of my maiden-head withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and I am like to pine in the languiſhing eſtate of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: made onely miſerable by the Eagle like pitch of my lofty deſires. In this manner ſpent ſhée away the day, till
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18921:7"/> the ſable Canopy of Heauen couered all the earth, a time of ſilence, a time of peace and reſt, a time that the eyes of all things cloſeth vp: yet ſléepe (the comforter of diſtreſſed minds, could not locke vp her eyes, for care had made them watchfull, griefe and diſtruſt like two dreadful companions waited in her chamber, euery idle imagination buzzed in her cares, the miſaduenture of her loue, fighting with all the miſdoubts of deſire, ſhée conſumed away the ſlow night, where euery minute ſéemed a day till morning came, and then like a carefull bride, ſhée cloathed her ſelfe in her richeſt attire, and by the Sunnes riſing came vnto the priſon, where ſhée found royall <hi>Richard</hi> vpon his Princely knée, pleading for his ſoules ſaluation, preparing himſelfe ready for his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-like combat, the night before brought to the Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall in a warrant from the Dukes counſel. Farewell vaine world (quoth he) thy flattering pompe hath béene to me, as water bubbles in a rainie day, or as Aprill ſhowers, or the flouriſhes of Gardens, ſudden and variable. Comfort me God, only in thy power is my deliuery, and without thy aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, this day is like to be my doomes day, and the laſt day of all my liues fortunes. At theſe words faire <hi>Clarabel</hi> ſunke into a ſwound, and ſo abounded in griefe, that her ſences were hardly recouered, but being againe come to her ſelfe, ſhée fell at King <hi>Richards</hi> knée, and in a moſt milde nature, ſpake as followeth.</p>
               <p>Moſt imperious Potentate, in whoſe happines conſiſteth my liues ioy, and in whoſe welfare my glory ſhineth: In thée thou pride of manhood, haue I built my hopes, and in louing thée, doo I purchaſe my fathers frowne, the Diademe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria.</hi> Now my right and patrimony doe I vtterly forſake, changing all my natiue honours into forraine hopes, and for thy ſake make my ſelfe a ſtranger to my countrey; euen in death ſprings my loue, and being dead, all earthly loues in me ends: Caſt me not off in diſgrace, but locke my true heart in thy Princely boſome, there kéepe it as an ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Iewell, pure, vnſpotted, and vnſtained, and tender as the budding Roſe, blaſted with the leaſt winde of thy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18921:8"/> diſlike: As for thy liues danger (ſwéet Prince) feare not, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen I ſée with a ſmiling countenance, promiſeth comfort, and legions of Celeſtiall Angels ſtand ready armed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thée from that hunger-ſtarued Lyon, prepared for thy liues deſtruction, a death diſhonourable, and vnfit for ſo roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all a perſon.</p>
               <p>In ſpeaking theſe words, ſhée tooke a gréene ſcarfe from about her iuory necke, and gaue it to King <hi>Richard,</hi> ſaying; Take this (ſwéet Prince) as the maiden-like promiſe of my lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and remembrance, weare it for my ſake, it may proue thy liues preſeruer, and the onely inſtrument to glut vp the Lyons gréedy Iaw, euen at that deadly minute, when he ſeaſeth vpon thy noble body. Pardon my immodeſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, for deſire and loue imboldens me, and all my maiden like baſhfulneſſe is aboliſhed, by the delightfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thy ſwéet ſelfe: For thée, and for thy loue, haue I ſold all my royall promotions; Then equall it (great King) that my affection bee not blaſted in the bloome, and I made the moſt wofull and diſpiſed Lady aliue.</p>
               <p>More would ſhée haue ſpoken, but that the gentle King tooke her from the ground, (yet knéeling) and with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull ioy of a curteous kiſſe, ſealed their lippes together, and after gratified her kindeneſſe with this louing diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Thou faire of all faires, thou paragon of beauty, in whoſe countenance (I ſée) ſits inthroniſed both vertue and modeſty, what vndeſerued fauour hath true iudging Heauen graced me with, in that thy inſpiring loue hath eluminated my clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Fortunes, now ſcowling with a diſmall countenance? Were the whole world mine, and I commander of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, yet ſhould all my dignities inrich thee, and my pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull regalties aduance thee to the imperiall eſtate of all earthly graces: This thy kindneſſe hath inchanted me, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſht my ſences, eleuated my ſoule, and of an earthly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, made my deſires immortall. Now flie I with the wings of good chance, which nothing can clip, but the ſharpe ſickle of deſpitefull death: For death (I know) with his gaſily
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18921:8"/> viſage, walkes here inuiſibly, with his tirannous command, ready to ſeaze vpon me: now is the houre of my liues aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the minute of that fearefull iudgement to be put in practiſe, to the appeaſing of Prince <hi>Phillips</hi> angry ghoſt.</p>
               <p>At this word ſpeaking, came in the Lord Marſhall with an armed guard, hauing a commiſſion to conduct King <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard,</hi> to a ſquare Court walled round: wherein was a Shée-Lioneſſe newly bereaued of her Whelps, to make her the more mankind: about which Court ſat the Duke and his Barrons in a gallery, to behold this vnnaturall tradegy: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which place being come, attended on a farre off, by the Princeſſe <hi>Clarabell,</hi> who with teares and ſighes did not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſolicet heauen for his ſtrengthner: all which forced pitty from the hearts of his enemies, and might haue mollified euen Tygers to relent.</p>
               <p>The two Engliſh Earles of Arundell and Oxford, his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued friends in miſery: High ſpirited, and full of reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, attended as before in their Friers habits, feeding him (as the beholders ſuppoſed) with the food of diuine counſels: but indéed with the animation of courage imbouldening him to take his fortunes patiently, and to thinke of the honour of his Countrey, by whoſe death England was widdowed, and his ſubiects made Kingleſſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe motions of incouragement, bred in his manly heart an inconquerable ſtrength, committing his life to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of fate: He ſtripped himſelfe from all Court-like ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliments, and in his cambricke ſhirt, with faire <hi>Clarabels</hi> ſcarfe wrapped about his arme, he ſtood prepared for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement of the remorſleſſe Lyon, which at the ſound of a Trumpet was let looſe, whoſe roares were as thunder from the clouds, and in whoſe grim viſage ſat the fearefull preſident of deſtruction; heart-breaking afflictions poſſeſt all his well willers, and the quiuering feare of his confuſion aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailed euery gentle eye, excepting <hi>Don Iohn</hi> and his aſſociats. To bee ſhort, the Lyon like the galfe of burning <hi>Acharon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18921:9"/> gaped to receiue the royal body of King <hi>Richard,</hi> who neither fearing death, nor the threatnings of tyranny, with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne courage, he moſt valiantly thruſt his arme (wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped about with faire <hi>Clarabels</hi> ſilke ſcarfe) into the gaping iawes of the ouer-furious Lyoneſſe, and by the force of his manhood to are out his ſauage heart, (yet leaping warme in his hand) and threw it at <hi>Don Iohns</hi> face, ſaying; Take that thou monſter of humanity, thou vnprincely Potentate, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thou ſéeſt hath defended me, to the wonder of ages, and thy vile diſgraces. Generall was the applauſe, the intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vexation of the wrathfull Duke, who like an vntamed Panthar, roſe from his ſeat, and in great wrath departed. King <hi>Richard</hi> ſéeing the Lioneſſe heartleſſe and liueleſſe, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the ground, to the great amaſement of all the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, yéelded the glory of this victory to the all-ſeeing prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Heauen. No little ioy had the two Engliſh Earles at this lucky ſucceſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but eſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ially the heart of diuine <hi>Clara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell</hi> danced in delights.</p>
               <p>Neuer had Lady the like cauſe of content, nor neuer La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more bound to thanke the Almighty powers of heauen. The relieued King, as the ignorant Lambe newly eſcaped from the bloody fury of the Wolie, with a countenance of a crimſon bluſh, declared the like gladneſſe, and in moſt kinde manner caſt the reflecting beames of his eyes toward <hi>Clara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> that ſhee well perceiued his curteous thoughts, and that gratefull thankes harboured in his Princely heart After the Dukes departure, the whole company ſoone broke off, bearing a ſecret fauour to the Engliſh King, who by faire <hi>Clarabell,</hi> the Earles of Arundell and Oxford, with ſome few other attendants of England, conducted him to a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate chamber, where after ſome refreſhing repaſt, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for England, but not meaning diſcourteouſly to leaue faire <hi>Clarabell</hi> behind, cauſed her to be attired in the habit of a Court Page, in a ſute of watched coloured veluet, to ſignifie the truneſſe of her loue, (for his ſake) in refuſing both Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Parents, and Kindred, and in this ſort to become
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18921:9"/> eſtranged from al her acquaintance. Such an imperious God is loue, and ſo commanding.</p>
               <p>The next day, vnknowne of any of the Dukes Court, but the Lord Marſhall, who aſſiſted them in all their procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, they tooke leaue of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and iournied toward <hi>England,</hi> where by the way King <hi>Richard</hi> and faire <hi>Clara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell,</hi> ſo ſecretly cloſed in affections, that her blooming bud of virginity was cropt, and the quittance of his loue-ſtroake ſealed in her wombe, a condition of ſuch content, as both pleaſure and deſires pleaſed each party. <hi>Clarabell</hi> in her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges attire, ſéemed in decentneſſe to excéed <hi>Ganemede, Ioues</hi> minion, or wanton <hi>Adonius</hi> the delights of <hi>Venus.</hi> Neuer had <hi>Paris</hi> the Troyan Prince, a greater conqueſt in the loue of faire <hi>Helena,</hi> then royall King <hi>Richard,</hi> of his admired <hi>Clarabell.</hi> Nature in her greateſt pride, framed this beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lady, as then the onely miracle of woman kind, he mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in her praiſes may write eternally. and thoſe laſting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports which aduanced ſo many Grecian dames, may now tell, and foreuer ſpeake off the ſuper-abounding graces of this faire Lady, that like vnto that Angell-faced <hi>Roſamond,</hi> wrought wonders in all eyes.</p>
               <p>No other comforts could poſſeſſe the Kings fancy, but this celeſtiall Lady, <hi>Europes</hi> admiration, and the worlds glory. In this rau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhing content ſpent they the time away, till happy Fortune ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them ſafely vpon the ſhores of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, whoſe ſwéet ſight was as ioyf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll to them all, as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of baniſht exiles to their w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed dwellings. This ioyfull day of their arriuall in England, was by the King and his Counſell canonized for a holy day, being the third of March, and to thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> time called Saint <hi>Richard</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Almanacks can yet teſtifie. King <hi>Richard</hi> hauing againe taken poſſeſſion of his Kingdome, and imperiall dignity, firſt gracing his two déere friend of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undell and Oxfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th commendable ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ancement for their loues and loyaltie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, then preparing in his City of <hi>London</hi> a royall lodging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his faire loue, néere vnto Cheape-ſide, called his Tower
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18921:10"/> Royall, Men royall (as he ſaid) in harbouring ſo faire a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramour, as was diuine <hi>Clarabell:</hi> In this place repaired he full often vnto her, and taſted of thoſe delights in nature, ſpotting her name with the title of a Kings Concubine. Long was he lulled in the cradle of pleaſures, careleſſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours aduancement, neglecting his countries fame: knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chiualry was conuerted to courtly dances, the lullabies of idle paſtimes rockt him aſléepe, till the diſgraces of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (receiued by his late impriſonment) awaked him, and called to armes: Then rowſing vp his Knightly courage, like Fames darling (being ſet amongſt his Barrons) he ſaid as followeth. Now Fire and Sword, the two inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of conſuming warre, ſhall forrage Auſtria, and by the Kingdomes ruine, worke me a ſwéet reuenge.</p>
               <p>My wrongs there receiued by the vniuſt decrées of <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> ſhall be quittanced with more then common ſpoiles, his Court ſhall ſwim in blood, his turrets flame in fire, heaps of mangled men, choake vp his ſtréetes, woe vpon woe, ſhall beſet him round.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Troy</hi> in her ten yéeres warres did not endure more cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities then <hi>Auſtria</hi> ſhall ſhortly ſuffer. Theſe and ſuch like high ſpirited ſpéeches, did King <hi>Richard</hi> ſpeake amongſt his Lords, to the great incouragement of them all, and ſo fired their luſty bloods, that well were they that could the moſt gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantlieſt ſet forth themſelues, and be the moſt forwardeſt in his noble enterpriſe.</p>
               <p>So deſirous were all eſtates, and ſo willing in this noble warre, that in leſſe then twenty daies the King was the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Generall of fifty thouſand Souldiers, all prouided ſo manfully, as if they had gone to make a new conqueſt of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. In which honourable iourney we will leaue him, and alſo the preparation that <hi>Don Iohn</hi> made to withſtand him, and his army, and ſpeake of the birth of <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> borne and kept ſecretly in King <hi>Richards</hi> Tower royall, with many other ſtrange euents that happened in the birth of this Princely babe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:18921:10"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the birth of <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> and how he came to be ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: and likewiſe how he was nurſed by the Queene of Fairies. Faire <hi>Clarabels</hi> lamentation for the loſſe of her young ſonne, and of other accidents.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ime the concluſion of all euents, brought to the worlds eye, the ſpringing wombe of <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabell,</hi> and néerely tenne Moones had now wandred out their wained courſes, when as therein King <hi>Richards</hi> royall fruit began to grow ripe and ready to fall, againſt which ioyfull houre, the carefull Lady ſpared for no coſt, and with her déere relenting heart ſolicited heauen for a happy deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the onely deſire of all weomen. I will not ſpeake of the tender natured Nurſes, the diligent Midwiues, nor the rich furniture prouided againſt that time: néedleſſe it were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the ſumptuouſneſſe of banqueting diſhes, nor the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of ſeruices belonging to ſo noble a buſineſſe, moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and gracious were all the procéedings of this her Chriſtian-like child-birth, not any diſpleaſing obiect hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her content, nor any way diſquieted her mind, but onely the want of her beloued, whoſe preſence in her eye had béene more delightſome then the pleaſures of <hi>Elizeum:</hi> Little ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſhée that King <hi>Richard</hi> had taken armes againſt her Father, the ſucceſſe whereof would haue but bred a ſtriſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt loue and nature: For nature in reaſon tooke her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers part, when as loue leaned to her Lord, yet ſhrowded were all imaginations in the cloſet of ſecretneſſe, and ſhe leaſt report thereof ſounded in her eares. Vnknowne were all theſe procéedings: For King <hi>Richard</hi> at his departure gaue commandement not to reueale them, till heauen had brought light to the fruit of her body. To be ſhort, the minute appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched of the Babes comming into the World, a ſweet tender
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18921:11"/> bloſſome, a moſt ioyfull wiſh for the pained Mother, who being borne, was to the beholders an excellent péece of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures worke-manſhip, vpon whoſe Infant brow ſat the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of good Fortune.</p>
               <p>After the Midwife (according to her manner) had trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vp the ſwéet Babe, and ſhewed him naked (to the other weomen her aſſociats) being a man child, vpon his breaſt it had the picture of a golden Faulkon, ſoaring ouer a moſt dangerous bridge, the which being ſhewed as a wonder in nature, the honorable Ladies in the Kings Court, by whoſe meanes it was generally reported through the Land, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter called in Chriſtendome, by the name of <hi>George</hi> Lord <hi>Faukonbridge:</hi> A title fitting for ſo noble an Impe of vertue, being deſcended from ſo royall a ſtocke (as was King <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> and faire <hi>Clarabell.</hi>) But to come to our purpoſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one moneth had run out thirty dayes, to the more then common griefe hf the mother, the tender Infant lying in his cradle, attended on by thrée carefull nurſes, euen at the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle houre of the night, when the ſiluer Moone in her greateſt glory danced on the chriſtall Seas, euen at that ſilent houre when the God of Dreames gouerned the World, there was heard in the chamber ſuch a melodious ſound of Muſicke, as if it had béene the harmony of Angels, or the ſinging Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins of Heauen, which in a bewitching manner ſo inchanted the wakefull Nurſes, that their eyes cloſed, and their ſences yéelded to ſound ſléepes.</p>
               <p>In this ſtill time of ſilence, came in the Quéene of Fairies, with a troupe of her inuiſible attendants, being the pretty dancing Elues of an vnknowne Kingdome, and ſtoale away young <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> out of his Princely cradle: whoſe miſſe (at his Nurſes waking) bred ſuch an amaſement amongſt them, as almoſt procured lunaſie, and forced them (like <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> froes) to runne madding vp and downe, not knowing in what manner to anſwere this their negligence: But yet this griefe of thiers, was but the induction to the true maze of calamity: the wofull mother (vnhappy <hi>Clarabell</hi>) made hapleſſe, miſerable, and moſt wofull, by the loſſe of this her
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18921:11"/> ſwéet Babe: this déere collop of her own fleſh, being ſo déere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fed with her owne blood, forty wéekes cheriſht in the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet of her wombe, and euen now (contrary to all expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) by the loſſe of it, to be bereaued of all worldly conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Oh thou vniuſt guider of mans life (quoth ſhée) what ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſinnes haue I committed againſt thy commanding dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? what blake offence hath now dimmed the cléere beames of mercy, that her eluminating glory is thus with-holden from me? Why had it not béene ſtrangled in my wombe, and made Deaths ſacrifice before it had ſaluted the Worlds eye? then for the want thereof had I not thus mourned, nor the title of a mother thus vnhappily wrought my hearts diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. Wéepe eternally (oh mine eyes) till you grow blind with lamentations; breake heart with ſwelling ſobbes, ſplit and burſt aſunder: Nothing but motions of croſſe chances intercepts my imaginations, conſuming ſorrow (like a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting tyrant) reuels in my diſtreſſes: Not any comfortable thought will in mercy ſeaze vpon my ſoule, pitty is fled, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe baniſhed, and gentle relenting paſſions, workes won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in my griefe-tired heart.</p>
               <p>Now this ſudden loſſe of her young ſonne, gaue her an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to deſire the preſence of King <hi>Richard,</hi> that in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſhée might a little eaſe her ſobbing boſome, and that an equall partition of griefe might be made betwixt them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering halfe of miſchances ſpight belonged to him, being the Father, and begetter of this blooming <hi>Faukonbridge:</hi> But when ſhée had intelligence of his departure for Auſtria, and of his reuenge pretended againſt her Fathers Country, and her natiue ſoile, and birthplace, a ſorrow beyond humane imagination aſſailed her heart, and a griefe (beyond the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Hecuba</hi> Quéene of Troy, hauing loſt one and twenty ſonnes) ſeazed vpon her ſoule: words were not ſufficient, teares of no force, ſighes ſobbing in blood, could not reueale the leaſt part of her bitter anguiſh: All the tongues that euer ſpake, all the pens that euer writ, nor all the bookes that euer was, could more tell, write, or containe, the true manner of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18921:12"/> the diſquietnes of this ſorrowfull Lady, the true patterne of griefe ſat heauily vpon her cloudy brow, and her eyes ſparke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as it were ſtreames of afflictions, day and night ſpent ſhée comfortleſſe away, food was as poyſon to her body, ſléepe as ſtrange company, loathſome: ſolitary ſilence wrought her the beſt caſe: nothing but idle viſions of diſcontent appeared before her: ſometime ſhée ſuppoſed that grim-faſt death with legions of wormes ſat deuouring the tender body of her yong bade: Sometime againe, ſhée imagined that an army of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels conducted the pretty Impe into the bleſſed kingdome of heauen: by and by againe, that wilde beaſts and rauing Foules, banquetted with his tender limbes: one while ſhée thought it lay ſtaruing in the fields frozen to death with cold, another while parched with the beames of the hot Sunne: A thouſand doubts had ſhée of the miſaduenture of this yong babe, beléeuing neuer to ſée it more, but that the doomes day of his liues ending had concluded all his Fortunes. Vpon which reſolution, ſhée exempled her ſelfe from the company of all people, excepting one ancient Gentlewoman, that daily attended in her Chamber, which brought her ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries as ſufficed nature, where like the picture of woe, vnbraſt, and diſrobde of all Lady-like attires, with diſheuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led haire hanging downe to the earth, we will leaue her in this her Tower-royall, ſo called by the reaſon of her roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all beauty, to the bitterneſſe of lamentations, fitting ſo ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull a Princeſſe, and ſpeake of the fearefull Fortunes, that the three nurſes had. After young <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> was in the poſſeſſion of the faire Queene, the eldeſt of theſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy nurſes, was a widdowed Lady of the Court, of a cleere complexion, faire and beautifull, whoſe face declared the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable ſhew of diſcontent. Poore ſorrowfull ſoule, after the young Infant was thus taken away, not knowing by what meanes, nor by whom, conſidering this her negligent care prooued a ſcandall to her reputation, ſhee exempted her ſelfe wilfully from the ſociety of people, and gaue her ſelfe to trauell, proteſting by the ſacred Maieſty of Heauen, to leaue no kingdome vnſearcht, nor no nation vnſeene into, till ſhee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18921:12"/> had found out young <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> and brought him againe ſafely vnto his carefull mother. The ſecond of theſe wofull nurſes, being a rich London Merchants wife, in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (in pennance for this her negligence) put her ſelfe vnto a heauy taſke, which was, to refuſe all the ioyes of marriage, not to take the fruition of her huſbands loue, not to ſléep vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon downy beds, but to reſt her ſelfe vpon the hard ground, making the duſty earth her pillow, where ſighes and ſobbes were her only companions, care her chamberlaine, and griefe her gardian, not any motion of delight could any more ſeaze vpon her heart, but all her meditations were ſtill made vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the wiſhed returne of young <hi>Faukonbridge.</hi> The third and laſt, but not the leaſt woful of theſe grieued nurſes, was a plaine, wholſome natured countrey-woman, of a complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion like vnto the Shepheards of Idea Mountaines, neuer more fairer were the tripping Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> ſporting vpon Cipreſſe bankes, nor neuer did nature frame woman more beautiful: vpon her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>héekes the lilly and the roſe ſtroue for ſupremacy, and the Vermillion bluſh of her beauty wrought deſire in all eyes, euen loue himſelfe danced in her countenance, yet all theſe rich gifts of nature, were quite blemiſht by the ſudden fright taken at the loſſe of this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der babe, whoſe abſence was as the bitter doome of death, and tranſformed all her wonted graces into pale feare, her face by it was changed into the ſhape of an aſhy viſage, or the wan countenance of a long dead body, all earthly conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ended, no hope had ſhée of her former ioy; diſpaire, blacke melancholy, deadly houres, and vnlucky thoughts harboured in her penſiue boſome, and by the loſſe of that ſweete Infant, (at whoſe birt heuen the Muſes dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,) all following good Fortune (was quite from this Nurſe exiled:) and as a puniſhment therefore, for her negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ſhée promiſed by a ſolemne vow made ſecretly with her owne heart, neuer to taſt other foode, but rootes, hearbes, and ſuch things as grew in the deſart woodes, nor neuer to drinke other liquour but cleere water,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18921:13"/> taken from running riuers, her companions were ſiluaine beaſts, and foules of the aire, which in their natures ſéemed to aſſiſt her in this her languiſhing life: long liued ſhée, with the reſt of her wofull partners, making their daily orazons for the ſwéet returne of this royall babe, for whom the whole land in great ſorrow mourned, whom we will leaue till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, and perſeuer in theſe following euents that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to King <hi>Richard,</hi> being wading in <hi>Auſtria</hi> through Seas of blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IIII. A wofull report of King <hi>Richards</hi> death. Of faire <hi>Clarabels</hi> lamentation for the ſame. Of her grieuous puniſhment by famine, and of other accidents.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter ſome little eaſe, like the ſwéet returne of ſome long abſent friend, had mittigated the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſorrowes of faire <hi>Clarabell,</hi> and that a little the remembrance of her Infants loſſe, ſome-what ceaſed her former laments, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to cheere her ſad heart with infuſing delights, that ſhée hoped to enioy by the ſwéet preſence of King <hi>Richard,</hi> wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hourely his company, little dreaming of his departure for <hi>Auſtria,</hi> but that he reuealed in his owne Court, to her great ioy, and his owne renowne, that at his firſt arriuall into her preſence, they might like <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> ſurfet in delight, or like <hi>Paris</hi> with his <hi>Helena,</hi> ſeale vp the true quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances of deſire, but all was not as ſhée wiſhed; for her hearts beloued, King <hi>Richard,</hi> flouriſhed in the royalties of <hi>Belonaes</hi> battels, wading in blood, and mounted vpon his vndaunted courſer, treading vpon mangled men, and marching after the cheerefull melody of warre.</p>
               <p>Which when the poore diſtreſſed Lady hard off, like a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned exile, baniſhed from all ſolace, ſhée exclaimed againſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18921:13"/> cruell deſteny, reuiling the angry Quéene of chance, accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all her hopes ominous, and her ſelfe the onely patterne of miſfortunes.</p>
               <p>Oh (quoth ſhée) what vnlucky planet predominated my birth? why was I borne to theſe miſeries? I liue deſtitute of friends in an vnknowne kingdome, diſhonoured with the title of a Curtizan, a pointing marke for vertuous Ladies, a ſtaine of woman-hood. Oh why was I borne to commit ſo foule a ſinne, that blemiſheth the glory of all Princes? Oh vnkind King <hi>Richard,</hi> now I ſée thou heapeſt vpon my backe a ſecond miſery, as thou haſt diſrobed me of virginity, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king me neither wife, widow, nor maide: ſo wilt thou or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane me, and intitle me by the name of a parentleſſe child: Woe vpon woe I ſée purſues me, calamity, diſcontent, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, deſpaire, yea, and all the miſeries that euer hapleſſe woman indured, now like whirle-winds, or tempeſtuous guſts, tumbles my care kild heart into the gulfe of vnpitied afflictions; be iuſt thou puniſher of blacke treſpaſſes, for my ſkarlet ſinnes knocke at Heauen gates for reuenge, and my deſert excéedeth <hi>Tarpies</hi> that ſold <hi>Rome,</hi> or the daughter of <hi>Ninus</hi> that betraied her fathers kingdome: for euen as the Viper I féed vpon my Parents woe, and as the curſe of nature, haue gloried in diſobedience, what good fortune can I challenge at the hand of deſtiny, in louing my fathers foe? yéelding that vnrecouered iem to his pleaſure, as being well beſtowed, might haue merited the worlds fame; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loſt to ſatiſfie his luſt, hath placed me (for a ſtrumpet) in the blacke booke of infamy? who can pitty my extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or what gentle eye will vouchſafe thereat to ſhed one teare? Teares from a remorſleſſe boſome are moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table dewes, and the ſwéet waters of hearts eaſe. Theſe, or ſuch like paſſions breathed ſhee from her diſcontented bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, which manner of lamentations once a day ſhée made to the ſightleſſe aire, till the time of ſixe moneths ouerpaſſed, at the end whereof, there arriued at her lodging, the two Earles of <hi>Arundell</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> newly returned from <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18921:14"/> being the onely counſellors to King <hi>Richard</hi> in all his procéedings, which two Lords brought the heauieſt newes that euer néerely touched <hi>England,</hi> ſuch newes that might euen haue broke a ſauage heart, newes of death and dolour, the ſignification thereof ſate like characters in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, and as it were made dumbe ſhewes of diſcontent, being with heauy countenances both come into the preſence of Lady <hi>Clarabell,</hi> the good Earle of <hi>Arundell</hi> ſaid as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Prepare (ſwéet Lady) with a gentle ſilence, to entertaine the wofulleſt tale that euer man at armes reported, for it tels of blood and death, and of the ruine of imperious ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignety. Know faire <hi>Clarabell</hi> that in one day by the fury of relentleſſe warre, thou haſt loſt both thy Father and thy Loue: Firſt thy Father when the battels ioined, cloſed with high ſpirited <hi>Richard</hi> in ſuch Princely reſolution, as euen fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his whole army with the liuely ſparkes of valour, and ſo proudly managed himſelfe againſt the gun-ſhot of chance, as if <hi>Hector</hi> and <hi>Achilles</hi> combated each other. On the other ſide Engliſh <hi>Richard,</hi> vnder whoſe enſignes our ſelues mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſo nobly, and ſo beyond expectation he behaued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as if <hi>Mars</hi> fought vpon the earth, both Heauen and Earth thundered forth their glories: Our two Armies were in number like the Campe of <hi>Scythian Tamberlaine,</hi> which (as it were) made the huge earth to grone.</p>
               <p>Neuer ſince the ten yéeres warres at <hi>Troy,</hi> did mans eye behold ſo numberleſſe a multitude, all valiant, feareleſſe, and aduenturous; we for the honour of England, they for the honour of Auſtria: Seas of blood couered the gréene fields, and the féete of horſes trampled out dead mens braines, the cries of dying ſouldiers ſéemed like thunder, and the chriſt al Aire ſpread forth her ſable Canopy, mourning at ſo wofull a maſſacre. After thouſands lay breathleſſe on the hungrie earth, glutted with the blood of ſo many thouſand Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, the victory grew ſo doubtfull, that Lady Fortune ſate wauering, not reſolued to what ſide to yéeld it: But woe is me, euen then the glory of both our Armies faded, and the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18921:14"/> eluminating light of two Princes was by conſuming death extinguiſhed: <hi>Auſtria</hi> loſt royall <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> your Father, and wee imperious <hi>Richard</hi> our King. Two ſuch loſſes, as <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> for them weepes blood, and may well conſume in griefe: Vpon whoſe deaths, both our Armies ſounded retreate, a peace proclaimed, and both their bodies had ſuch funerals as befitted the perſons of ſuch high dignities.</p>
               <p>Our Leaders and Captaines (hauing loſt their Princely Generall, imbraced peace, and with the Swordes ſheathed, Cullors rolled vp, and with heauy hanging countenances, are now arriued in <hi>England,</hi> where (with the generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the whole Nobility) we haue crowned <hi>Iohn</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, King of this Countrey, whom in all allegiance we will henceforth honour and obey. More would they haue ſpoken, but the griefe of <hi>Clarabella</hi> ſo abounded, that ſhee could keepe ſilence no longer: but in great extremity of paſſion burſt out into theſe ſpéeches.</p>
               <p>Héere (quoth ſhée) let the World end; for the terrible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of woe (like the raging <hi>Ocean,</hi>) breakes in, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowes all my ioyes: I haue loſt my Father, Friends, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Kinred, Acquaintance, yea, and my Child: and the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of all Iewels, Royall King <hi>Richard,</hi> by whoſe death I am made moſt vnfortunate.</p>
               <p>Deſcend ſome vnlucky ſtarre, fall vpon me you fatall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and ſtrike me blinde, that my ſightleſſe eyes may behold no further miſeries. Where art thou miſchance? afflict me with ſome fearefull confuſion; that like the wife of <hi>Oedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> the whole World may report my ſhame. Heauens bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings (I ſée) hath refuſed me, and like an out-caſt loaden my blood-red heart with more then earthly ſorrow, and with which it is rent, torne, and moſt lamentably tormented.</p>
               <p>At theſe wordes ſhée offered to teare forth her owne eyes, had not the gentle aduice of the two Earles perſwaded her to patience, which ſhée willingly imbraced, and ſo for that time parted company: Shée to her ſorrowfull cloſet, they to the new refined Court, where (after K. <hi>Iohn</hi> had intelligence of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18921:15"/> the ſucceſſes of <hi>Clarabella,</hi> ſent to her a commiſſion of baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with a commandement that no Engliſh ſubiect vpon paine of death, ſhould giue her any ſuſtenance of food, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by her wantonneſſe might be ſcourged with pining famiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: a grieuous and ſeuere penance, deſeruing the name of heathen tyranny. But ſuch was the indignation of King <hi>Iohn,</hi> and ſo violent in wrath, that euen death quittanced her fauourites. (Poore mappe of miſery!) ſhée was forced to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake Courtly faſhions, and to exchange her coſtly attires in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to beggers wéeds: ſhée that had wont to féed vpon the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of dainties, was now ſufficed with courſe ſeruices, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then with thoſe things that ſatiſfied hunger-ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued hounds: many a little dogge (in the laps of young wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons) had more abundance of food then this gallant Lady had. Day by day walked ſhée comfortleſſe vp and downe the ſtréetes, moning her owne miſfortunes, yet vnpittied, and left to her complaint. Night by night wearied ſhée out the long houres with remembrances of her former life, where euery minutes thought begot new griefe, and euery thought of new griefe almoſt ſplit her heart: ſighes were as common obiects to ſatiſfie her diſcontents, being diſpleaſed with all things ſhée caſt her eye vpon. Not any comfortable motion could ſhée entertain, wearied ſhée grew of the wanton world, not knowing which way to turne her ſelfe: Miſery followed her vp and downe; when ſhée remembred <hi>Auſtria</hi> her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Kingdome, diſobedience cut her heart, when ſhée cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to mind her Virginities wracke, a thouſand woes (ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with repentance) ouerwhelmed all inſuing hopes, and almoſt caſt her into deſperation, ſhée ſuppoſed pitty to be deafe, and the tender remorſe of humane gentlenes to bée ſhut vp againſt her. Shée that lately abounded in plentuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, now liued in want of a beggars pittance, ſhée onely fed vpon ſorrow: Sighes were her food, and teares her drinke, wo, miſery, and penury, in moſt extreame manner, tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her pining carkaſſe, till pouerties thinne countenance conuerted her roſe-like chéekes into a pale complexion: her
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18921:15"/> hollow eyes ſéemed like the empty cels of death, ſorrowes badge (which is a wrinckled brow, declared to the world pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull proſpects, to the wringing handed griefe of the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which were not a few in number.) See into this globe of miſery (you blazing ſtarres of Chriſtendome) you flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Damſels, that ſels your bodies pleaſures to make your ſoules blacke: You that liue by the ſpoiles of youth, making a paſtime of wantonneſſe, gathering to your ſelues the hated names of common Curtizans, corrupted with moſt vile diſeaſes, loathſome and full of leproſie. To ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe many woes, poore <hi>Clarabell</hi> indured in this pining pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, we will leaue her lying vpon the bare earth (by a ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle gate) onely for an example to all ſuch careleſſe liuers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too ſimple a lodging for a Princes daughter, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the ſuccéeding euent of young <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> and thoſe thrée vnhappy Nurſes, ſéeking for this Babe of honor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. How young <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> was found by King <hi>Iohn</hi> in his hunting. How hee preſerued his Mothers life (vnknowne to him: And likewiſe how he ſuccoured the three Nurſes; and of the three gifts giuen him by the <hi>Queene of Fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow muſt we ſuppoſe <hi>Time</hi> (in his ſwifteſt courſe to runne along) and ſome certaine yeares to paſſe ouer the head of <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> where (taking leaue of the <hi>Fayry Queene,</hi>) he had thrée of the richeſt gifts giuen him by her, as neuer worldly man was owner off. The firſt was a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made him of the Lyons ſkinne, that his Father <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Cordelyon</hi> ſlew in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> of vertue ſo precious, that the wearer thereof ſhould neuer faint in courage, but euer continus Victor in all atchieuements. The ſecond a purſe of gold, of ſuch a plentifull treaſure, that can neuer grow
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18921:16"/> empty, but as it is taken forth, the vertue thereof reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth it againe, by which meanes it continues full. The third a ring of ſuch ineſtimable price, that by the touch ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of healeth all diſeaſes (neuer ſo dangerous and vncurable.) Theſe were the bleſſings of the <hi>Fayry Queene</hi> beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this yong gallant, which he receiued as his patrimony, and kept them as the onely gifts of good Fortune.</p>
               <p>Thus being of the age of fiftéene yéeres, he continued in the woods (like vnto a ſauage ſatyre) vnacquainted with worldly people, rouing vp and downe, vntill ſuch time as King <hi>Iohn</hi> of England, (his vnckle by the Fathers ſide) found him in his wild quality: but ſéeing him repleniſhed with ſuch lineaments of nature, ſtrong, and ſturdy, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed enſuing honors: He tooke him to his kéeping, and gaue him in charge to an ancient Noble man of his Court, to be trained vp, and taught perfectly his naturall Engliſh tong, which hee moſt ſpéedily accompliſhed to his high renowne: whereupon the King ſoone aduanced his eſtate, and made him groome of his priuy chamber; but he hauing the lofty ſpirit of Knight-hood ſpringing in his breſt, aimed at nobler aduentures, and to winne credit by the ſtrength of his body, deſired the Kings leaue to depart his Court, and to trie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne atchieuements in the honour of God and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: which princely requeſt did not a little content the King, whereupon he gaue him a horſe well furniſhed with all the abilliments fitting ſo reſolued a Gentleman, and with all graced him with the picture by nature ſet vpon his breſt. Thus after leaue taken, like one of Fames darlings, this knightly <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> in the ſpring-time of his youth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelfe to fortunes fickle fauours, where after he had trauelled ſome few daies iournies from the Engliſh Court, he arriued at the gate of an Hoſpitall, whereat lay <hi>Clarabell</hi> his vnknowne mother, begging for reliefe, with theſe lines grauen ouer her head vpon the wall in capitall letters, according to King <hi>Iohns</hi> commandement.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:18921:16"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A Princes daughter by the Kings decree,</l>
                     <l>Here pines in care, ſtand ſtill, and paſſe not by,</l>
                     <l>Till this poore map of perfect miſery,</l>
                     <l>With wringing hands heau'd vp to heauen high,</l>
                     <l>Tels how her wanton life in ſinne was ſpent,</l>
                     <l>And why ſhee thus makes wofull languiſhment.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Pitty her not, her life is ſtaind with ſhame,</l>
                     <l>By her a Kingdomes ruine was begot:</l>
                     <l>Luſt and deſire hath blotted her good name,</l>
                     <l>And true repentance muſt make cleere that ſpot.</l>
                     <l>To ſuccour her is death, authority commands,</l>
                     <l>Againſt which power, lift no preſumptuous hands.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>Lord <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> hauing read this ſuperſcription, in pitty rued her eſtate, not knowing her to be his mother, for as yet his parents were vnknown to him, yet harbouring in his breaſt noble thoughts, he could not chooſe but extend cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity vnto her, and being the firſt of his aduentures, and the maiden-head of his mercy, the firſt good déed that euer he did, therefore he willingly alighted from his palphrey, and in tender pitty tooke the halfe ſtarued Lady by the hand, ſaying; If thou béeſt deſcended royally, as theſe letters witnes that thou art, I am bound in all knightly curteſies to defend thée, and in maugre of blacke Fortunes ſpight, ſuccour thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed eſtate, as it ſéemes now the worlds out-caſt. Tell me faire Lady thy name, thy birth, and abode, and as I am ſworne true Knight, I will be thy champion, and conduct thée ſafely into thine owne countrey. Theſe gentle promiſes made by Lord <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> aſpired new life into her fading body, who with a chéerefull countenance ſpake as followeth:</p>
               <p>Deare Knight thy deſert I know not, but ſurely thou ſéemeſt to be gracious in all thy procéedings, and deſires not I know to inforce a Lady, to ſpeake of that which will breake her heart to remember: Yet becauſe thou promiſeſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18921:17"/> me thy gentle aide, to deliuer me from this miſerable vale of woe, and ſet me wiſhedly vpon the ſhore of my natiue kingdome, vilely diſhonoured by my wilfull follies: Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand then I was borne in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> my name <hi>Clarabell,</hi> Princely my Father, from whom I diſobediently fled for the loue of a Northerne Monarke, vnto whom I yéelded vp the pleaſures of my virginity, the loſſe whereof made me, (though no wife) yet an vnhappy mother: for which blacke ſinne I am now thus puniſhed. Queſtion no further ſwéet Gentleman, for the reſt will bereaue me of life, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy noble diſpoſition, be my gardian, and conduct me to my natiue countrey, and the rewarder of all good déeds, will quittance your curteſies. Indéed faire Lady (quoth he) as our oathes in Knight-hood be ſo to doe, ſo in performance thereof I will aduenture my life, though it be to the Kings high diſpleaſure. So taking her vp behind him vpon his horſe, he carried her to the next towne, and there both chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her pining body with comfortable victuals, and after cloathed her in ſuch garments as befitted the degrée of a Gentlewoman, and ſo ſet forwards towards Auſtria, ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſlow time away with pleaſing diſcourſes, little thinking of the néere alliance that was betwixt them two, the one the mother, the other the ſonne: but heauen meaning to ſhew a wonder in their liues, would not as yet ſuffer their kindreds to be brought to light.</p>
               <p>So trauelling on as I ſaid before, they were intercepted by a moſt ſtrange obiect, which were thrée moſt diſtreſſed creatures, ſéeming by their attires to be weomen, and the thrée nurſes (in former times) of young <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> which <hi>Clarabell</hi> full well knew, but that ſhée feared to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered. The good Knight being ſtil pittifull, beholding their miſeries, the one dumbe, the next blind, and the third lame. Thrée woefull companions, whom age and time had thus croſſed with heauy calamity, hee like a true godly minded man, with that ring which the Fairy Quéen had giuen him, cured all their maladies, the vertues of it being ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18921:17"/> that it no ſooner touched their diſmembred bodies, but immediately they were all made perfect, the lame could goe, the blinde ſée, and the dumbe ſpeak: which miracle done by Lord <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> according to the will of heauen, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced teares through extreame ioy, to fall from the three recouered Nurſes eyes, deſiring the maker of all things to reward his curteſies. The good Knight, not onely cured their griefes, but gaue them great ſtore of gold out of his moſt plentifull purſe, another gift from the Fairy Quéene by him receiued. Now theſe thrée new reuiued weomen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſafe and ſound, no ſooner departed, but faire <hi>Clarabell</hi> greatly deſired to be Miſtreſſe of two ſuch precious Iewels as this Ring and the Purſe was, whereupon in moſt gentle manner ſhée intreated Lord <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> to beſtow them vpon her, that for his ſake ſhée might were them, a fauour to her heart (as ſhée ſaid) more inualuable then was the Iewell that <hi>Marke Anthony,</hi> gaue <hi>Cleopatra</hi> Quéene of Egypt, gifts in his imagination, priſed aboue the worlds Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, yet being loath to deny her requeſt, he moſt willingly gaue her them, and with his owne hand putting the Ring vpon her pretty finger, and tying the rich purſe by her come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſide, he ſaid, Neuer let Knightly proweſſe aduance my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, nor record my liues fame in the booke of memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time, but let me die blotted with cowardice, the foule ſtaine of matchleſſe Knighthood, when I refuſe to accompliſh the leaſt motion of your Lady-ſhips deſire: for in your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſhines honourable graces, and promiſeth dignified vertue. To whom <hi>Clarabell</hi> with a modeſt behauiour an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in this ſort: And much were I too blame (Sir knight) if I ſhould not ſeeke by deſert to requite your kindneſſe, and vile ingratitude as a diſgrace to my calling, might be well allotted to my ſhare: If time and good fortune euer aduance me to my former eſtate, I will make thy credit equall Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian <hi>Achilles,</hi> and cauſe the worlds famous antiquaries to ſignifie thy martiall condition: thou haſt bewitcht mee with thy vertues, and with the chaine of manly carriage bound
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18921:18"/> my life to thy ſeruice: Reſeruing my honour, I humble my ſelfe to thy nobleneſſe, which honour onely I once ſubmitted to a King, the fruit thereof might I but liue to ſée, my earths content were then growne to a perfection. Liuing, or dead, great <hi>Ioue</hi> protect him: this is my orizon to heauen, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this doe I daily meditate. Theſe miſticall ſpéeches of hers, might haue lighted the fire of diſcouery, but that blind fate would not as yet haue them knowne. Theſe and ſuch like, were the pleaſurable diſcourſes betwixt theſe two tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellers, with the which they ſpent away many a long day and weary night, without any aduenture worth the noting. But as Fortune is not alwaies ſmiling, here ſhée beganne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to frowne, and to croſſe their deſires with an vnlookt for chance: For vpon a hot ſummers day, when the bright Sunne in his greateſt glory ſhined in the horizon, in a moſt intollerable heat, the poore Lady wearied with trauell, ſat her downe to reſt in a pleaſant gréene ſhade of trées (where dallying with the Ring vpon her lap) ſhée fell faſt aſléepe, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which ſwéet ſlumber, there came a huge blacke Rauen ſoaring by, and thinking the yellow Ring to be ſome prey, which lay vpon her lap, with her tallents catcht it vp, and therewithall flew quite away, to the great amaſement of Lord <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> ſtanding by the ſléeping Lady as her gardiant, and being loth to looſe ſo rare a Iewell, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon his Stéed, and in moſt ſwift manner followed the Rauen ſo farre, that he quite loſt the preſence of faire <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabell,</hi> whom (for a while we will leaue ſléeping) and ſpeake what ſtrange aduenture happened to this noble Knight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18921:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. How Lord <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> was found by the Moores, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the King of Morocco. Of his aduentures in that Kingdome. The lamentation of <hi>Clarabell</hi> for her paſſed life: and how in penance thereof, ſhee builded a Monaſtery for the receit of poore Pilgrims.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Oble minded <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> followed the flight of this rich priſed Rauen, carrying in his beake the worth of a Kings ranſome, not reſting nor pitching vpon any trée or branch, till ſhée had let the Ring fall into the Sea, which ſtruck ſuch terrour to the heart of <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konbridge,</hi> (then ſtanding vpon the ſhore, ſéeing the euent) that he almoſt caſt himſelfe after it into the waues, but that better graces guided him, and hope of better Fortunes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained his deſperateneſſe. Standing thus amaſed, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to mind the loſſe of <hi>Clarabella</hi> (whom he had left com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe behind) ſléeping in a gréene ſhade of trées, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how, nor which way to returne backe, belieuing neuer more to behold her Angelicall countenance: Therefore like a mournefull Traueller (looſing himſelfe in ſome deſart wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe) he breathed out this vnpittied lamentation:</p>
               <p>Many and vnlucky are my firſt aduentures (quoth he) at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended on by croſſe chances, and vntoward procéedings; no motion of reliefe can I premeditate vpon. For I am come by ill Fortune into a place of deſolation, not frequented by the habitation of man: Here liues nothing but gréene bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied Serpents, roaring Wolues, and beaſts of fearefull ſhapes, ſuch as may well terrifie the proudeſt courage: Here ſounds no other Ecchoes but the croakes of Rauens, night-Owles, cries, and the bellowing of vntamed Tygers, ſuch as thunders forth nothing but ſounds of death and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: here is no other food to ſuſtaine nature, but wild hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks, henbane, and ſuch impoiſoned wéedes, the onely ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18921:19"/> of blacke inchanters, witches, and charmers, the aire ſéemes to be corrupted, and the earth caſts vp putrifying ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, worſe then the ſmoaking lake where <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorra</hi> ſtood. In this manner complained he for the ſpace of thrice twelue houres, looking euery houre to be deuoured by wild beaſts, but that his Lyon-like garment which hee wore, made them thinke him to bee one of their number, which ſauage creatures in tame manner lodged by his ſide.</p>
               <p>As he thus betwéen feare and hope, expected preſent death, hee beheld a Turkiſh galley houering by the ſhore ſide, the Captaine whereof (being a noble minded Gentleman) at the firſt ſight of young <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> caſt a Land, where (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding his diſtreſſes) tooke him aboord, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nlookt for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, not a little reioiced him: but being ſo happily preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from death, moſt willingly ſubmitted to their mercies, they being Moores, he a Chriſtian: they miſbeléeuing, he true in faith, they blacke, he faire, two extreame contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: yet when theſe Heathen people beheld his face ſtored with ſuch maieſty, reſembling the beauty of his Creator: they admired his Angelike countenance, neuer before that time ſéeing a man of his colour, but all blacke like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, therefore ſuppoſing to haue found ſome heauenly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, they preſented him to their King, as then kéeping his Court ſome foure miles diſtance from that place, on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of the Sea, (being but a créeke of the maine Ocean) in a moſt ſumptuous Pallace, for brightneſſe like to the Tower of the Sunne.</p>
               <p>The Morrocco King with his blacke countenance, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing himſelfe in his royall throne, with great admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on receiued Lord <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> not as a Captiue, or a chai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Galley-ſlaue, but like the Darling of Maieſty, or as the Paragon of Fame, ſent from Heauen to glorifie his Court. Legions of reports might wee make of his entertainement with the Morocco King and his Nobles, who eſtéemed him rather to be ſome God, then a worldly man, more dignified honours heaped they vpon his backe, then euer that country
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18921:19"/> gaue vnto a ſtranger. The wealth of that Kingdome made they his treaſury, and maſſes of Indian pearles lay ſtill at his commandement, the time of his abode there paſſed on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace, and iollity of his life made ſeuen yéers but as a month-</p>
               <p>Which being ouerpaſſed, it was his chance vpon a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne feſtiuall day, which was the birth day of their King, onely once in ſeauen yéeres ſolemnized, to behold the chiefeſt of the Kings Nobility in their richeſt ornaments, going as it were on proceſſion in the honour of their Prophet <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi> Placing him (as it ſéemed in heauen) to the high diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of the Chriſtians God, whoſe wrath and indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the whole Worlds confuſion, and whoſe fauour the preſeruation of man-kind.</p>
               <p>This God and liuing Power, was the Patrone of Lord <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> by whoſe fauour he hoped to conquer Fats, and ſubdue Kingdomes: This God when he ſaw him thus highly diſhonoured, fury poſſeſt him, and to the great diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of all that heathen Nation, he deſperately tore downe the picture of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and with his kéene edged Semitary cut it in ſmall pieces, to the great amaſement of the Kings Nobility, who in gréedy reuenge furiouſly ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him altogether (like a number of whelps vpon a prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lyon) who ſo Lyon-like behaued himſelfe, that in leſſe then halfe an houre, hee left breathleſſe vpon the blood-died earth, more then ſixe and twenty of the Kings Nobles, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing here his vnconquerable valour, procéeding from the vertue of his Lion like garment, which the Fairy Quéene had giuen him.</p>
               <p>At this bold enterpriſe performed with his owne hand, he cauſed the Moores to ring forth their Alarum Bels, and to fire their Beakons, to raiſe vp their country forces, thinking that heauen had thither ſent a confounder of mankind, and that by his onely meanes their kingdome ſhould be ſubdued.</p>
               <p>This matchleſſe enterpriſe performed by noble minded <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> did not a little perplex the King, nor no idle feare aſſailed his mind, but ſuch a fright as made his very ſoule to tremble: wherefore to rid his kingdom from preſent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18921:20"/> danger, in moſt kind manner he proclaimed truce, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblingly applauded Lord <hi>Faukonbridg</hi> for this deſperate attempt: (and though to his griefe of mind) with faire and princely promiſes, he perſwaded this Engliſh Gallant to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part his Country: and the more to aduance his deſerued ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, the King beſtowed vpon him twelue barrels of good red gold, and withall a ſhippe well furniſhed, to conduct him home into his owne Country. Which kind fauour was moſt gratefully accepted off by noble <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> who leauing the Morocco Kingdome, put himſelfe to Sea, committing his fortunes againe to the merciles waues, but making the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot and Marriners beléeue, that the twelue barrels of gold, were but twelue barrels of red lead: a commodity moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in his natiue Countrey. The Pylot ſuppoſing no otherwiſe, ſailed amaine with proſperous wind towards the Northerne nations. In which ſucceſfull iourney, we will leaue now Lord <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> and returne to his vnknown Mother (Lady <hi>Clarabell</hi>) whom we left as you heard before, ſleeping vnder a ſhade of trées, where Lord <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> beganne to follow the chace, after the vnlucky Rauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clarabell</hi> as we ſpake of before in her ſwéete ſleepe, little dreaming of the abſenee of <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> at her awaking, both miſt him, and the ring; two loſſes ſo precious, as euen cauſed ſorrow to reuel in her boſome, that Ioy was a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and content exiled; diuers were the doubts ſhee had of his miſaduentures, one while ſhee ſuppoſed death like a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant had poſſeſt him, another while ſhee feared the breach of his promiſe, and that he had ſecretly fled from her, bearing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with him the inchanted Ring: Now one thing, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, not knowing what to coniecture, but when ſhee ſaw her ſelfe quite bereft of his ſweet preſence, the onely preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of her life, exempted from al hope of his recouery, in great griefe of minde, ſhee betooke her ſelfe to trauell, and ſo with weary ſteps followed on the firſt path ſhee found, wherein ſhee wandred day and night, receiuing little reſt, and leſſe food, making this ſorrowfull mone vnto her ſelfe. Oh thou
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18921:20"/> iuſt doome (quoth ſhee) of all offences, will thy heauy wrath be neuer mittigated? ſhall this my pining puniſhment ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer end? ſhall woe vpon wo ſtill purſue me? weep in teares oh mine eyes, be neuer dried faire lamentations: euen at that houre when I hoped all ſorrowes to be finiſhed, began new griefe, when in looſing my Sonne, I found a Friend, whom now wanting, I find eternall cauſes of diſcontent: It cannot be poſſible, but that ſome diſmall miſchance hath befallen him, or ſome vnlucky <hi>Lot</hi> deceiued me of him, there is no likely-hood of his ſelfe-wild departure, for in his breaſt he harboured thoughts of true humanity, honour guided him, and vertue was his friend: how can it then be that of his owne accord he is departed? Surely ſome vnlucky euent hath befalne him: therefore, oh my heart ſob in griefe, and for his ſake make thy life but a pilgrimage of woe, conſume in care, waſte with wéeping, for I haue loſt the Paragon of Knight-hood, whoſe countenance promiſed me to aduance my deſired hope, and bring me ſafely vnto the ſhoare of my natiue Countrey: but ſéeing dole and diſcontent hath croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all my good Fortunes, I will for his ſake, with the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of my neuer emptied purſe, receiued from him, built vp a Monaſtery, and in the ſame (like a Monaſticke Nunne) ſpend out my daies in the ſeruice of that God that hath thus croſſed me, and there be a continuall comforter of diſtreſſed Pilgrims, and warfaring trauellers, hoping that if life be in my déere friend, he will once againe arriue in that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py place, and once more ſatiſfie my thirſting eye with his Princely perſon. Being thus reſolued, ſhée trauelled ſome thrée moneths iourney from the place, where ſhée loſt her déere friend the Lord <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> and there cloſe by the Sea ſide, ſhée builded a moſt ſtately Monaſtery, relieuing ſtill the wants of ſuch diſtreſſed trauellers as paſſed that way, yéelding as well lodging, as meat and drinke, to ſuch as ſtood in néed thereof: For the maintenance thereof, ſhée had her inchanted purſe ſtill ready furniſhed; thither reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted people of all degrées, thither came Princes, Monarkes,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18921:21"/> and maieſticke Kings, that trauelled in deuotion to the ſhrine of Chriſt in Ieruſalem. Thither came worthy cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, Knights errant, and ſuch as ſought for knightly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuements: t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ither came religious Church-men, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and holy minded men, zealouſly ſéeking by Pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to wipe away worldly offences, thither came Plowmen, Shepheards, Fiſhermen, and ſuch as were numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the common people, thinking thereby to obtaine ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution for their miſdéeds, euery one offering in zeale vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her great ſtore of riches, whereof ſhée had little néed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it meritorious to giue towards the maintenance of ſo vertuous a cuſtome. Amongſt which number of Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, there was one <hi>Peter</hi> a Fiſherman, that in deuotion of minde, preſented vnto her a moſt dainty Fiſh called a Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin, a preſent more fitter for a Prince, then ſuch an humble minded woman as ſhée was, whoſe humility almoſt in that Countrey purchaſed her the name of a Goddeſſe: This gift from the fiſherman was by her moſt curteouſly receiued, and moſt bountifully requited with great ſtore of golde, which ſhée tooke from out her inchanted purſe: Herewith was old <hi>Peter</hi> well pleaſed, and the Lady better contented, for in the Dolphins belly ſhée found the ſame Ring, which the Rauen let fall into the Sea, the ſame Ring after which Lord <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> ſo vnhappily followed, the ſame King that by the precious touch of it healed all diſeaſes. In this accident fortune ſhewed the pride of her glory, and brought more ſtrange admiration into the heart of <hi>Clarabell,</hi> then euer ſhée expected: but being poſſeſt thereof, ſhée verily belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that noble <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> lay intombed in the watery Kingdome, and that neuer more the conſolation of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſhould in ioyfull manner delight her deſirefull eye: pale death (as ſhee ſuppoſed by the finding of this Ring) had made prize of his life, too rich a Iewell, as ſhee ſaid, for this vngratefull World, therefore in the true zeale of heart, and in remembrance of his worthineſſe, ſhee cauſed a Faulkon of Gold to be ſet vpon the top of the Monaſtery, wherein
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18921:21"/> ſhée dwelled, the bright eluminating colour thereof ſhined into the Sea, and was euer after that made a marke, or a guide for Mariners to ſaile by. Alſo like a curteous Lady, to quittance old <hi>Peter</hi> the fiſhermans rich preſent, by good Fortune beſtowed vpon her, ſhee canoniſed the Monaſtery, and called it after his name, Saint <hi>Peters Hermitage</hi> a place of charity, and a receit for all ſuch as wanted maintenance. After this, thouſands of oppreſſed people in this place found ſuccour, Pilgrims and weary trauellers here freely found lodging: Widdowes and ſuccourleſſe Children, here taſted bounties liberality, maimed Souldiers, and ſuch as loſt their limbes in the ſeruice of their Countrey, here ſlept vpon downy beds, more ſofter then naples ſilke: Blind, deafe, and dumbe, in this place found helpe, not any diſeaſed creature went from hence vncured, all which by this vertuous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, was onely done in charity for Gods ſake, and to appeaſe the torments of his ſoule, that in guiding her to her natiue Countrey, loſt his deere life. Wherefore from this day, to her liues departure, ſhée deſired the fellowſhip of vertue, abandoning all immodeſt behauiour, vowing her ſelfe to the ſeruice of Heauen, and good déeds, in which ſhée continually ſtriued to excéed all others of her time: which good deuotions we for a while will ouerpaſſe; and report of other delightfull accidents, agréeing to the courſe of this our Hiſtory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. How Lord <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> loſt himſelfe in a barren Iland. His meanes of recouery. The finding againe of <hi>Clarabell.</hi> How theſe two were made knowne to each other. And of the great ioies betwixt the mother and her Sonne.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow is it time to report againe of Lord <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konbridge,</hi> and his fortunes on the Sea, and how his ſhip loaden with his barrels of golde, lay houering on the billowes, many a day ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting a proſperous wind for England, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18921:22"/> obtained none: For fate and good Fortune croſſed their hopes, and want of victuals ſo oppreſſed them, that hunger almoſt ſurpriſed their liues, and like a pittileſſe Tyrant would grant them no remorſe: twiſe ſixe moneths conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued this their extremity, to the terror of all good men, a death bringing horror both to man and beaſt. At the laſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had made many ſubmiſſiue prayers to God for a good winde, <hi>Aeolus</hi> ſet open his brazen gates, and ſent them ſuch a gentle gale, that they in thrée houres ſayling, arriued vpon an Iland ſo barren, that therein they found no other thing to ſuccour their diſtreſſes, and preſerue them from fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhment, but onely freſh water, with the which they ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſtored their ſhip, giuing Heauen thankes for ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a fauour. But this ſuffiſed not the deſires of noble <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konbridge,</hi> hoping to find better reliefe for him and his men, reſolutely aduentured further vp into the Iland, to diſcouer if he could wherewithall to vittaile his ſhip. But woe is me to report it, this aduenturous Gentleman tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelled ſo farre, that he loſt his way, not being able to returne backe vnto his company, by which meanes he was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſtay all night vpon the top of a trée, for feare of wilde beaſts, whereof the Iland was full. But now marke how vnlucky all things fell out, the ſame night the wind roſe, and ſo violently droue the ſhip from the ſhore, that the Pilot was inforced to leaue Lord <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> a Land, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit his Fortunes to the Sea, where before day light they were caſt vpon the coaſt where Saint <hi>Peters</hi> charitable Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitage was ſcituated, they being Infidels and Mooriſh na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured people, neuer expected the ſafety of Lord <hi>Faukonbrdge,</hi> being a Chriſtian, but left him comfortleſſe in the barren I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and caſt a ſhore where faire <hi>Clarabell</hi> abode, where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a Land, deſired her for his ſake that created her, to affoord them ſome reliefe, whereby their liues might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and their ſhip ſufficiently repleniſhed with food fitting their intended voyage. Pittifull <hi>Clarabell</hi> good Lady<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhée greatly reioiced that it lay in her power to furniſh their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18921:22"/> wants, moſt willingly gaue them entertainement, and yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them ſuch refreſhing comforts, as preſerued both their ſhip and liues from periſhing. Likewiſe they meaning to expreſſe no vngratefull thankes for ſo kinde a fauour, as an humble ſigne of good will, curteouſly beſtowed vpon her, the twelue barrels of gold which Lord <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> reported to be red lead, all which according to her gentle nature, noble minded <hi>Clarabell</hi> receiued. So parting with thankes to each other, the Pilot returned to Morocco, very ioyfull for the riddance of Lord <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> their Countries ſuppoſed enemy, and ſhée no leſſe delighted in the performance of her bountifull charity extended to the preſeruation of ſo many dying men. All this while Lord <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> remained in the barren Iland, almoſt hunger-ſtarued for want of food, in which place was nothing found to ſatiſfie his gentle na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but the fleſh of wilde beaſts which hee killed with his owne hands, which (for want of fire) hee roſted in the ſun, and with the ſame, (to his content) made more pleaſinger banquets, then when he feaſted in the <hi>Morocco</hi> Court, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly patience chiefly guided him, but being thus loſt, and exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the ſociety of humane creatures, he liued a long time in the woods, in ſuch penurie and want, that his ſtrength began to faile, ſickneſſe grew on, and danger of life tormented him for want of naturall ſuſtenance, cauſed a grieuous kind of leproſie to grow quite ouer his body, in ſuch ſort, that his Princely countenance was ſuddenly chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into a moſt vgly viſage, and pale death as it were ſate perching vpon his heauie brow, betwixt life and death, hee ſate him down vpon the root of a dead withered trée, making this complaint vnto himſelfe. If euer pitty (quoth he) entred the celeſtiall gate of Heauen, or euer remorſfull mercy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly lookt into the poore eſtate of a miſerable Gentleman, then by this my liues ruine, may be ſéene the true patter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of calamity: woe vpon me, croſſe vpon croſſe, and extremity vpon extremity, makes a vnity, and all conſpires together to worke my good Fortunes confuſion. Here am I now left
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18921:23"/> in a wilderneſſe of deſolation, friendleſſe without comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not knowing which way to get forth, but committed to the vile tyranny of vntamed Tygers, euen ready to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tombe my dying body within their blood-thirſting bowels, a graue moſt vnfit to cloſe vp my new created life. In ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king theſe words, he heard from a farre, as it were out of a hollow vaute, a voice ſounding forth theſe ſpéeches: <hi>Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konbridge,</hi> riſe vp and follow me: Fate and good chance will proſper thée. This ſéemed to be the voice of the Fairy Quéene, his old Nurſe, being ſtill moſt carefull of his liues preſeruation, as it was indéed; which no ſooner ecchoed in the eares of Lord <hi>Faukonbridge,</hi> but he aroſe from vnder the trée where he lay, and being ready to goe forward all weake and ſickely as he was, he eſpied before, one of the Fairy Inſtruments, which was an <hi>Ignis Fatuis,</hi> the fire of deſtiny, or a going fire, which by nature fully leadeth wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring trauellers out of the way. This as his guide went ſtill before him, he with a ſlow pace followed after, not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by any miſaduenture, till hee came to the Sea ſide, where being ioyfully arriued, in good time he beheld a Barke ſailing by, to which he made ſhew of entertainement, as one deſirous to be taken into their ſhip, and to be conducted in to ſome better reſting place: both his motions and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the Mariners ſoone perceiued, whereupon they ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his deſire, and within few <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aies ſet him ſafely vpon the next inhabited kingdome, which was the happy place where <hi>Clarabell</hi> affoorded ſuch bountifull liberality. Being thither come, the Countrey people and ſuch as beheld his perplexed eſtate, led him as diſeaſed as he was vnto <hi>Clarabels</hi> Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, where being arriued, and ſtanding ſhaking at the gate, he deſired for his ſake that pardoneth all ſinnes, and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all good déeds, that ſhée would with the oyle of her ſkill balme his grieued paines, and with the mercy that ſhée frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſtowes vpon diſtreſſed ſoules, cure his malady. Gentle <hi>Clarabell</hi> at this his humble requeſt, called him in, leading him vp inio a cloſe chamber, prepared onely for the comfort
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18921:23"/> of ſuch wofull creatures, in which place after ſhée had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his drooping ſences, and by the vertues of the ſame ring (he in former times had beſtowed vpon her) recouered his wonted health, ſhée ſéeming in his face, that beauty repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed againe, which before that time ſhee ſuppoſed to haue ſéene, and calling to remembrance his former Fauour, ſhee perfectly knew him, whereupon ſeeking to imbrace him, ſhee ſounded in his armes, and for the ſudden ioy that he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by his ſtrange returne, lay for a good ſeaſon in a dying trance: but being by great diligence recouered, they recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted each to other the wonderfull Fortunes paſſed betwixt them, from the firſt looſing of one another to that houre, Likewiſe he ſpake, how hee neither knew Father nor Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor from whence he deſcended, and withall (opening his boſome) he ſhewed her the golden Faulkon, by nature pictured vpon his breaſt, which when ſhee beheld, her very ſoule, as it were eleuated it ſelfe to Heauen, and more then mortall ioy poſſeſt her heart. By this ſhee knew him to bee her onely Sonne, begot by King <hi>Richard Cordelion,</hi> King of England, and ſo made it knowne vnto him. Which when good Lord <hi>Faukonbridge</hi> vnderſtood, he in the true duty of a Sonne newly created, downe vpon his knées, craued her bleſſing, and in great humility of mind gaue thankes to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, in that it was his Fortune to defend his mother in an vnknowne Land, from ſo many dangers, and ſhee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe made many deuout Orizons to God, that in his mercy had ſo preſerued them, and in this manner brought them moſt ſtrangely together.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:18921:24"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18921:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
